Register of the Vera Cattell collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Vera Cattell collection
1767-1986
2000C2
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 1 card file box (4.0 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia relating to aspects of Russian imperial and military history, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, and Russian émigrés in China and elsewhere.
Cattell, Vera
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists primarily of papers belonging to Grigorii Konstantinovich Bologov, chairman of the Russian Emigrants' Association of Shanghai, and concerns the evacuation and resettlement of White Russian refugees from China. The bulk of the series under that name relates to the emigrants' stay at a refugee camp on Tubobao Island in the Philippines under the auspices of the United Nations International Refugee Organization. It includes material about conditions in the camp, lists of refugees, and correspondence with American and Philippine camp authorities, as well as correspondence related to efforts to obtain permission for emigration to the United States, South America, and Australia. Of special interest is an extensive correspondence of Archbishop John of Shanghai and San Francisco. Also included are the founding documents and minutes of meetings of the Russian Emigrants' Association in Shanghai and Tubobao.
Of particular interest in the subject file are the correspondence and personal papers of Prince Iskander Riza Kuli Mirza, as well as printed copies of orders issued by him as Commander of the Ekaterinburg Garrison in 1918-1919, during the Russian Civil War. The file also contains the business papers and military medals of Leonid Vishnevetskii, his business partner.
The photograph file contains a large leatherbound album celebrating the 100th anniversary of the Imperial Guards Regiment (Sobstvennyi Ego Velichestva Konvoi), in which the prince served and which includes informal photographs of the Russian imperial family.
Furthermore, the collection contains the commission and passport papers of Karol de Perthees, royal cartographer to King Stanislaw August Poniatowski of Poland, to be found in the oversize file. Karol de Perthees was probably the most prominent 18th century Polish cartographer. He was born in Dresden, the capital of the Saxon-Polish monarchy, the illegitimate son of the Russian envoy in Dresden and later in Warsaw, baron Herman Kayserling. Perthees lived and worked in Warsaw from 1764 until 1798. After the third partition of Poland he moved to Wilno where he devoted his time to entomology. (He compiled 9 vols. of Insecta Polonica et Lithuanica.) Perthees' detailed maps of Poland, later reprinted in Berlin and Petersburg, were commonly used during Napoleon's invasion of Russia. He was married to Jozefa, the middle daughter of Bernardo Bellotto Canaletto, the court painter of King Stanislaw August.
China.; Russia--History, Military.; Russia--History.; Russia.; Russians--China.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.
- Russian Refugees from China File, 1937-1973 (Box 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Announcements, appeals, clippings, correspondence, financial records, founding documents, lists, memoranda, minutes of meetings, petitions, reports, personal papers, clippings and other printed matter related to the evacuation and resettlement of Russian refugees from China. Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - General
    - Clippings, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Individual petitions for emigration, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Lists of evacuees, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Bologov, Grigorii (G. K. Bologoff), Chairman of the Russian Emigrants' Association
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1949-1973 (Box-folder 1: 4)
      - Bogen, E. (Special Delegate for Resettlement, IRO-UNEC, Tubobao, Philippines)
        - General (Box-folder 1: 5)
          Includes instructions of American government agencies and International Refugee Organization, 1949-1951
        - Resettlement in Germany, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 6)
      - Delovaia Komissiia Pomoshchi Tubobavtsam (Viktor Korostylev), 1949-1950 (Box-folder 1: 7)
      - John (Maksimovich), Archbishop of Shanghai and San Francisco
        General note
        See John (Maksimovich), Archbishop of Shanghai and San Francisco/Correspondence
      - Komissiia Po Okazaniiu Pomoshchi Pereseleniiu Russkikh Bezhentsev (Committee on Resettlement of Russian Refugees) (Viktor Borzov), 1949-1950 (Box-folder 1: 8)
      - Modest, Hieromonk, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 1: 9)
      - Rossiia, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 10)
      - Tinio, Capt., 1949 (Box-folder 1: 11)
      - Zaitsev, Pavel ( Russkaia Zhizn'), 1949 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Memorandum to American government, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Personal papers, undated (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Reports
      - "Possible Improvements of Legal Position of the Russian Emigrants,", undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
      - "Russian Emigrants' Association,", undated (Box-folder 1: 16)
      - "Russian Political Emigrants in China,", undated (Box-folder 1: 17)
      - "Ruinous Position of White Russian Emigrants in China,", 1946 (Box-folder 1: 18)
      - "On Persons Twice Displaced" and "On Camp Conditions in Tubobao,", 1949 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - China Realty Co., 1937
    See PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Diplomatic missions in Shanghai. List of personnel, 1948 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Federation of Russian Charitable Organizations in the United States. Minutes of meeting, 1948 April (Box-folder 1: 21)
    See also Bologov, Grigorii/Correspondence/Komissiia Po Okazaniiu Pomoshchi Pereseleniiu Russkikh Bezhentsev
  - I.R.O. Camp, Tubobao Island, Cuiuan, Samar, Philippines
    - Correspondence, reports and clippings related to Senator William Knowland's visit to the camp, 1949 (Folder 1: 22)
    - Draft for constitution of Arbitration Board, undated (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - Lists of refugees
      - Arrested for various misdemeanors, undated (Box-folder 1: 24)
      - Members of R.E.A. Concert Band, undated (Box-folder 1: 25)
      - Residents in the camp, 1949 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
    - Medical documents, 1949 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Press release, 1950 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - John (Maksimovich), Archbishop of Shanghai and San Francisco
    - Clippings (Box-folder 2: 5)
      Includes newspaper interviews, 1949
    - Correspondence with Grigorii Bologov
      - Incoming, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 2: 6)
      - Outgoing
        - 1949 (Box-folder 2: 7)
        - 1950 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Sermon, Christmas, 1949 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Komissiia Po Okazaniiu Pomoshchi Pereseleniiu Russkikh Bezhentsev (Committee on Resettlement of Russian Refugees). Announcements and forms, 1950 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Orthodox Church in China, Chancery. Announcements, directives, and correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Rossiiskaia Emigrantskaia Assotsiatsiia (Russian Emigrants' Association)
    See also Bologov, Grigorii/ Correspondence
    - Address to John (Maksimovich), Archbishop of Shanghai and San Francisco, 1949 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Announcements, 1950 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Appeals for aid in the resettlement of refugees
      Includes correspondence, reports, and printed matter
      - General, 1948-1952
        - General (Box-folder 2: 14)
        - Argentina (Box-folder 2: 15)
        - Australia (Box-folder 2: 16)
        - Brazil (Box-folder 2: 17)
          Includes correspondence of V. Reyer
        - International Refugee Organization, Geneva, 1949 (Box-folder 2: 18)
          Includes 3,000 signatures of camp residents
        - Italy (Box-folder 2: 19)
          Report on refugee camp
        - Philippines (Box-folder 3: 1)
          Includes correspondence with president's office
        - United States
          See also Bologov/ Correspondence/Bogen, E.
          - General (Box-folder 3: 2)
          - List of refugees who applied for immigration into the U.S. (Box-folder 3: 3)
      - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1949
    - Correspondence, reports, and minutes of meetings related to Grigorii Bologov's business travel
      - Philippines, 1949 (Box-folder 3: 4)
      - United States, 1950
        - General (Box-folder 3: 5)
        - List of contributors (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Donations file, 1950 (Box-folder 3: 7)
      Typescript
    - Financial records, 1947-1950 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Letter of gratitude to the American people, undated (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Membership registration blanks and list of members, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1948-1950
      - General (Box-folder 3: 11)
      - Executive Committee (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - Printed matter
      See OVERSIZE FILE
    - Replies to enquiries related to members, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Statutes, founding documents and other material related to the organization in Shanghai, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 3: 14-17)
  - Russian Center of San Francisco. Miscellany, 1952 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - St. Tikhon's Orphanage and Seminary of St. John the Baptist (Box-folder 3: 19)
    Includes correspondence between the Chancery of the Orthodox Church in China and the Tubobao Camp Administration, and a list of pupils and staff, 1949-1950
  - Surinam. "Vestnik Russkikh v Surinami,", 1952 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - United States. Congress. House of Representatives, Report No. 2187, 81st Congress, 2nd Session, 1950 June 2 (Box-folder 3: 21)
- Subject File, 1913-1931 (Box 4)
  Correspondence and personal papers of Iskander Riza Kuli Mirza and Leonid Vishnevetskii; Russian paper money and government bonds; documents related to the Russian Revolution and Civil War. Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Bonds - Russia, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Georgievskii Komitet Ego Imperatorskago Vysochestva Velikago Kniazia Mikhail Aleksandrovicha. Statutes and membership list, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Iskander Riza Kuli Mirza
    See also OVERSIZE FILE
    - Correspondence and clippings related to court case re inheritance, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Personal papers, including military service records, 1913-1915 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Orders issued as Commander of Ekaterinburg Garrison, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 4: 5)
      Printed sheets
    - Telegrams
      - Mariia Feodorovna, Empress of Russia, 1913-1914 (Box-folder 4: 6)
      - Mikhail Aleksandrovich, Grand Duke, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Paper money - Russia (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Petrogradskii Sovet Rabochikh i Soldatskikh Deputatov. Order No. 1, 1917 March 1 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    Printed copy
  - Sobstvennyi Ego Velichestva Konvoi (Imperial Guards Regiment). Orders, 1916 February (Box-folder 4: 10)
    See also PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Tsarskoe Selo. Clipping, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Vishnevetskii, Leonid. Contracts and other documents related to platinum mining, 1903-1916 (Box-folder 4: 12-13)
    See also Photographs and Memorabilia
- Photographs, 1929-1937 (Box 5-6)
  72 prints related to Russia before the Revolution; 1 album of 22 postcards depicting uniforms of the Imperial Guard; 1 large leatherbound album celebrating the 100th anniversary of the Imperial Guards (Sobstvennyi Ego Velichestva Konvoi) and containing 100 prints depicting the regiment and the imperial family
  - 1 print depicting Saint John of Kronstadt, undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - 19 prints depicting Emperor Nicholas II, undated (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - 5 prints depicting Empress Alexandra, undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - 15 prints depicting Grand Duke Alexis, undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - 18 prints depicting the imperial family, undated (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - 6 prints depicting the imperial family in informal military settings, undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - 1 postcard depicting Emperor Nicholas II, commemorating his death, 1929 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - 1 print depicting Leonid Vishnevetskii, 1927 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - 4 prints depicting miscellaneous Russian subjects, undated (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - 1 print depicting the Declaration of Trust of the China Realty Co., 1937 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - 1 photograph copy of a Chinese document, undated (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Album of 22 postcards, illustrating uniforms of the Imperial Guard, undated (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Album celebrating the 100 th anniversary of the Imperial Guard (Sobstvennyi Ego Velichestva Konvoi) (Box 6)
    Includes 100 prints showing members of the regiment in dress uniform and on parade. Also includes formal and informal photographs of the imperial family, n.d.
- Oversize File, 1767-1915
  - 1 print depicting the class of the Khristchanskii Soiuz Molodykh Liudei in Harbin, China, 1936 (Box 7)
  - Printed matter
    - Jiganoff, V. D., Russkie v Shankhae, undated (Box 7)
    - Komitet po Sooruzheniiu Khrama Pamiatnika Moriakam Pogibshim v Voinu s Iaponiei v 1904-1905 gg., Khram Pamiatnik Moriakam Pogibshim v Voinu s Iaponiei v 1904-1905 gg (Box 8)
      Printed copy, 1915
  - Personal papers of Karol de Perthees (1740-1812), royal cartographer/geographer to King Stanislaw August Poniatowski of Poland (Box 9)
    Includes his Commission as lieutenant in the Polish Crown artillery, signed by Count Aloisius Bruhl, 1767; a passport for travel to Elblag, East Prussia, signed by King Stanislaw August; his commission as colonel, signed by King Stanislaw August, 1783; extract from a register of the nobility of Wilno Guberniia confirming titles of the Perthees family, with wax seal of Emperor Alexander I, 1812
  - Watercolor depicting a rider (Iskander Riza Kuli Mirza?) on horseback, undated
- Memorabilia, 1920-1928 (Box 10)
  Medals received by Leonid Vishnevetskii for service in the Polish Army, 1920-1928